# SHORT CURRICULUM VITAE (updated 18 July 2019) – Reynaldo C. Ileto

## **PERSONAL**

Name: Reynaldo Clemeña ILETO
Date & Place of Birth: 3 October 1946, Manila
Citizenship: dual Australian/Filipino
Email: rey.ileto@anu.edu.au

URL: https://researchers.anu.edu.au/researchers/ileto-rc

https://anu-au.academia.edu/ReynaldoILETO

### **CURRENT ACADEMIC AFFILIATION**

Honorary Professor, College of Asia and the Pacific, Australian National University & Member of the ANU Emeritus Faculty

#### LAST POSITION HELD BEFORE RETIREMENT

Professor, Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences, National University of Singapore

### ACADEMIC AWARDS AND DISTINCTIONS

2018: *Gawad Pambansang Alagad ni Balagtas* ("Disciple of Balagtas National Award"), Union of Writers in the Philippines (Unyon ng mga Manunulat sa Pilipinas, UMPIL)

2018 ff.: Membership in the Emeritus Faculty, Australian National University

2012: Gawad Tanglaw ng Lahi ("Guiding Light of the Nation Award"), Ateneo de Manila University

2012: University Teaching Excellence Award, National University of Singapore

2011: Grant Goodman Prize in Philippine Studies (Association for Asian Studies, USA)

2009: *Pasyon and Revolution* voted as one of the 10 most influential books on Southeast Asia (*Sojourn* journal, Institute of Southeast Asian Studies)

2003: Academic Laureate, Fukuoka Asian Culture Prizes 2003

1999: Philippine National Book Award (First Prize, History, for Filipinos and their Revolution)

1999: Featured in Kelly Boyd (ed.), *Encyclopedia of Historians and Historical Writing*, Vol. 1 (Fitzroy Dearborn Publishers)

1997: John A. Burns Distinguished Professorship in History, Univ. of Hawaii at Manoa

1986: Masayoshi Ohira Memorial Foundation Prize for Pasyon and Revolution

1985: Benda Prize in Southeast Asian Studies (Association for Asian Studies, USA)

1984 -85: Tañada Distinguished Professorial Chair in History, De La Salle University, Manila

1967-70: Humanities and Social Sciences Scholarship, Cornell University

1967: Cum Laude (2<sup>nd</sup> in graduating class), Ateneo de Manila University

### **EDUCATIONAL ATTAINMENT**

- Elementary (1959) and High School (1963): Ateneo de Manila
- B.A. cum laude, Ateneo de Manila University, 1967, major in Humanities
- M.A., Cornell University, 1970, major: Southeast Asian History; minor: Modern Chinese History
- Ph.D., Cornell University, 1975, major: Southeast Asian History, minor 1: Southeast Asian Anthropology; minor 2: Modern Chinese History

## **ACADEMIC APPOINTMENTS**

2019 (Aug. Oct.) Adjunct Senior Fellow, RSIS, Nanyang Technological University, Singapore

2015-2020: Honorary Professor, College of Asia and the Pacific, ANU

2018 (Aug.-Oct.): Adjunct Senior Fellow, S. Rajaratnam School of International Studies, NTU

2014-2017: Adjunct Senior Fellow, S. Rajaratnam School of International Studies, Nanyang Technological University, Singapore

2012-14: Associate Senior Fellow, Institute of Southeast Asian Studies, Singapore

2001-2012: Professor (with tenure), Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences, NUS [2003-05: Head, Department of Southeast Asian Studies, NUS]

1996-2007: Reader (with tenure), Faculty of Asian Studies, ANU (on leave 2002-07)

2000 Sept.-July 2001: Visiting Senior Scholar, Institute for the Languages and Cultures of Asia and Africa, Tokyo University of Foreign Studies

1997: (Fall Semester) John A. Burns Distinguished Visiting Professor, Department of University of Hawaii at Manoa

1991-92: Visiting Research Scholar, Center for Southeast Asian Studies, Kyoto University

1986-95: Reader in History (tenured), James Cook University, Australia

1985 (Sept.) Scholar-in-Residence, Rockefeller Foundation International Conference Centre, Bellagio, Italy.

1984-85: Associate Professor, History Dept., University of the Philippines

1977-84: Assistant Professor (tenured in June 1979), University of the Philippines

1984 (Jan. to Dec.): Associate Professor (tenured), History Dept., De La Salle University, Manila (concurrent appointment with the University of the Philippines)

1980 (Jan.-June): Visiting Fulbright Lecturer, University of California at Santa Cruz

1982-83: Philippine Studies Fellow and Visiting Lecturer, Asian History Centre, Faculty of Asian Studies, ANU.

1974-76: Postdoctoral Fellow, Dept. of Pacific and Southeast Asian History, Research School of Pacific Studies, Australian National University (ANU)

1970-71: Teaching Assistant, Dept. of History, Cornell University

### MISC. ADMINISTRATIVE POSITIONS

2003-05: Head, Southeast Asian Studies Program, FASS, NUS

1998: Head, Asian History Center, Faculty of Asian Studies, ANU

1996-99: Director, Graduate Program in Southeast Asian Studies, ANU

1990: President, Philippine Studies Association of Australia

1984: Chairman, Curriculum Committee, History Dept., De La Salle University

1979: Chairman, Committee on Research, Division of Social Sciences, College of Arts and Sciences, UP-Diliman

1970: President, Cornell Filipino Club

1970: Chairman, Organizing committee, First Conference of Filipino Students in the U.S., Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.

1966-67: Associate Editor, Heights literary magazine (Ateneo de Manila University.)

### ACADEMIC JOURNALS (CURRENT BOARD MEMBERSHIP)

Asian Perspectives in the Arts and Humanities, Ateneo de Manila University (Member, Board of Editors)

Historical Bulletin, Philippine Historical Association (Member, Editorial Board)

Journal of Southeast Asian Studies, National University of Singapore (Member, Honorary Advisory Board)

Philippine Studies, Historical and Ethnographic Viewpoints, Ateneo de Manila University (Member, Editorial Advisory Board)

Social Science Diliman: A Philippine Journal of Society and Change, University of the Philippines (Associate Editor)

#### RESEARCH

#### **Research Interests:**

Religion and popular movements in Southeast Asia; The Philippine-American war; Tagalog popular literature; Comparative Spanish, U.S., and Japanese colonial discourse and practice in the Philippines; Politics of health and sanitation; Debates on history within Southeast Asia; History and nation-building in the Philippines; Historians and public intellectuals in Southeast Asia; Historical dimensions of the China-Philippines conflict in the South China (West Philippine) Sea.

# **Forthcoming Publication**:

The Philippines, 1898-2016: Empire, Nation-building, and the "Unfinished Revolution." Singapore: Institute of Southeast Asian Studies

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

### **Monographs**:

2017. Knowledge and Pacification: On the U.S. Conquest and the Writing of Philippine History. Quezon City: Ateneo University Press.

2007 Magindanao, 1860-1888: The Career of Datu Utto of Buayan. Manila: Anvil Press (Vintage Series), 2007 (revised edition of the 1971 Cornell monograph).

2004. Dioramas: A Visual History of the Philippines, Manila: Ayala Foundation.

1999. Knowing America's Colony: A Hundred Years from the Philippine War (The Burns Chair Lectures, 1997). (Occasional Papers Series, Center for Philippine Studies, University of Hawaii at Manoa)

1998. *Filipinos and Their Revolution: Event, Discourse, and Historiography*. Quezon City: Ateneo University Press, 1998; Honolulu: University of Hawaii Press 1999; 3<sup>rd</sup> printing, 2003.

1993. *Discovering Australasia: Essays on Philippine-Australian Interactions*. Edited by Reynaldo C. Ileto and Rodney J. Sullivan (Townsville: James Cook University).

1979. *Pasyon and Revolution; Popular Movements in the Philippines, 1840-1910*. Quezon City: Ateneo University, 1979, 1997 (under University of Hawaii imprint), 8<sup>th</sup> printing 2011. A Japanese translation, with an introduction by Yoshiko Nagano and new preface by the author, was published by Hosei University Press in 2005.

1971. *Magindanao, 1860-1888: The Career of Datu Uto of Buayan*. Cornell Southeast Asia Program, Data Paper #82.

### **Articles and Book Chapters (selected):**

- 2019. "The Southeast Asian Context of the Filipino Struggle for History and the Rise of the Philippine Historical Association," *Historical Bulletin*, vol. 52 (forthcoming).
- 2018. "The Centennial of 'Cacique Democracy'-- Constructing Politics in a Time of Pacification," in Celina S. Cristobal (ed.), *The Adrian E. Cristobal Lecture Series 2010-2017* (Manila: Inyan Publishers, Inc.)
- 2017. "Horacio de la Costa, SJ, the Filipino Historian, and the Unfinished Revolution," in *Reading Horacio de la Costa, SJ: Views from the 21st Century*. Edited by Soledad S. Reyes (Quezon City: Ateneo de Manila University Press, 2017): 117-142.
- 2017. "Independence and Friendship: Shared Histories in the China-Philippines Sea Crisis," in *Southeast Asia and China: A Contest in Mutual Socialization*, edited by Lowell Dittmer and Ngeow Chow Bing (Singapore: World Scientific Publishing, 2017): 71-92.
- 2016. "Historians and 'Unfinished Revolution': Trajectories of Philippine Historical Writing from the U.S. Conquest to the Present," *Historical Bulletin* (The Philippine Historical Association), vol. 50, 2016: 1-14.
- 2014. "Father and Son in the Embrace of Uncle Sam," *Philippine Studies: Historical and Ethnographic Viewpoints*, vol. 62 no. 1: 67–114
- 2013. "Nation and Empire in the Intellectual Biographies of Southeast Asian Scholars," *Asian Studies* 59,3-4(Oct 2013): 9-16.
- 2011. "El debate sobre el 'Proyecto de Ley Rizal' de 1956 y la influencia de los tres imperios en Filipinas (The 'Rizal Bill' Debate of 1956 and the Specters of Three Empires in the Philippines)," in Maria Dolores Elizalde and Josep Delgado (eds.), *Filipinas: Un Pais entre Dos Imperios* (The Philippines: A Nation between Two Empires). Barcelona: Edicions Bellaterra.
- 2011. "Reflections on Agoncillo's *Revolt of the Masses* and the Politics of History," *Tonan Ajia Kenkyuu (Southeast Asian Studies)* 49, 3(Dec. 2011), Kyoto University Center for Southeast Asian Studies.
- 2011. "Scholarship, Society, and Politics in Three Worlds: Reflections of a Filipino Sojourner, 1965-95," in Goh Beng-Lan (ed.), *Decentring & Diversifying Southeast Asian Studies: Perspectives from the Region*. Singapore: Institute of Southeast Asian Studies.
- 2011. "Wars with the US and Japan, and the Politics of History in the Philippines," in Kiichi Fujiwara and Yoshiko Nagano (eds.), *The Philippines and Japan in America's Shadow*. Singapore: National University of Singapore.
- 2011. "A Tagalog Awit of the 'Holy War' against the United States. 1899-1902," in Keith Thor Carlson, Kristina Fagan, and Natalia Khanenko-Friesen (eds.), *Orality & Literacy: Reflections across Disciplines*. Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 247-79.

- 2010. "Heroes, historians and the New Propaganda Movement, 1950-1953." *Philippine Studies* 58, 1-2(2010), 223-38.
- 2007. "World War II: Transient and enduring legacies for the Philippines." In David Koh Wee Hock (ed.), *Legacies of World War II in South and East Asia*. Singapore: Institute of Southeast Asian Studies: 74-91.
- 2005. "Philippine Wars and the Politics of Memory." *Positions: East Asia Cultures Critique*, 13, 1 (Spring 2005): 215-235.
- 2002. "The Philippine-American War, Friendship, and Forgetting," in Angel V. Shaw and Luis H. Francia, editors, *Vestiges of War: The Philippine-American War and the Aftermath of an Imperial Dream 1899-1999.* New York: NYU Press: 3-21.
- 2001. "Orientalism and the Study of Philippine Politics," *Philippine Political Science Journal* 22, no. 45, 1-32. (Reprint of part 3, *Knowing America's Colony*, 1999)
- 1997. "Outlines of a Nonlinear Emplotment of Philippine History," in David Lloyd and Lisa Lowe (eds.), *The Politics of Culture in the Shadow of Capital: Worlds Aligned*. Duke University Press.
- 1995. "Cholera and the Origins of the American Sanitary Order in the Philippines," in V. Rafael, ed., *Discrepant Histories: Translocal Essays on Filipino Cultures*, Philadelphia: Temple University, 1995, pp. 51-81.
- 1992. "Religion and Anticolonial Movements" in Nicholas Tarling (ed.), *The Cambridge History of Southeast Asia* vol.2, pp. 197-248.

## **PUBLIC LECTURES AND CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS (recent)**

## 2019

- 1. Keynote lecture: "Voices from the UP Diliman of the 1970s: The Correspondence of a Defector from Loyola Heights," University of the Philippines, Quezon City, 22 February.
- 2. Plenary lecture: "The Multiple Roles of Emilio Aguinaldo in the History of Nation-building," International Conference on Aguinaldo @ 150, Lyceum of the Philippines University, Cavite campus, 20 March.
- 3. Public lecture: "Gen. Emilio Aguinaldo and the Contested Narratives of Philippine History (ca. 1948-1983), PHA Colloquium, Pamantasan ng Lungsod ng Valenzuela, Bulacan, 14 June.

## 2018

1. Public lecture: "*Dark Ages* in the History of the Philippines: Tyrants, Martyrs and Saviors in the Construction of a National Narrative," Sophia University, Tokyo, 7 December.

#### 2017

- 1. Plenary lecture: "The Southeast Asian Context of the Filipino Struggle for History and the Rise of the PHA," International Conference on "The Malay World: Connecting the Past and the Present," Philippine Historical Association, Manila, 14 Sept.
- 2. Paper presentation: "Teaching Southeast Asia in Four Countries," Busan University of Foreign Studies (S. Korea), 26 May

#### 2016

- 1. Public lecture: "The Philippines in the 20th Century: Child, Friend and Foe of Empire," Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prize Committee, 23 July
- 2. Special lecture, "The Philippines in Asia: The Uses of History in Regional Conflicts," Kyushu University, 22 July
- 3. Public lecture: "Revisiting the Place of Japan in the Story of the Philippine Nation," Japan Foundation, Tokyo, 20 July
- 4. Public lecture on Fr. Horacio de la Costa, SJ, Commemorative Lecture Series, Ateneo de Manila University, 11 February
- 5. Public lectures (2), "Conversations with Professor Reynaldo C. Ileto," Chiang Mai University, Thailand, 30 March and 1 April

### 2015

- 1. Paper presentation: "Contest in the South China Sea: Shared Histories," Southeast Asia Conference, Kyoto University, 13 Dec.
- 2. Commemorative lecture: "In His Own Words: General Miguel Malvar and the Southern Tagalog Resistance," Santo Tomas, National Historical Commission of the Philippines, 28 Sept.
- 3. Keynote lecture: "Historians and 'Unfinished Revolution': Trajectories of Philippine Historical Writing from the U.S. Conquest to the Present," 60<sup>th</sup> Anniversary Conference, Philippine Historical Association, Manila, 27 Aug.

### 2014

- 1. Public lecture: "The Revolution of 1896-1902 and the Politics of Philippine History," Universitas Negeri Yogyakarta, Indonesia.
- 2. Public lecture: "The Centennial of Cacique Democracy in the Philippines," Adrian Cristobal Memorial Lecture, University of the Philippines, 30 Aug.
- 3. Paper presentation: "The Cacique in Philippine History and Politics," AAS-in-Asia Conference, NUS, 17 July

## 2013

- 1. Keynote lecture: "Nation and Empire in the Intellectual Biographies of Southeast Asian Scholars," Japan Association for Asian Studies 60th Anniversary Symposium, Rikkyo Univ., Tokyo, June.
- 2. Plenary lecture: "History as Theater of War: Case Studies from Southeast Asia," Philippine Political Science Association annual convention, Batac, Philippines, April.
- 3. Keynote lecture, "Southeast Asians Rising: Revisiting the Early Pioneers," 5<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Southeast Asia, University of Malaya
- 4. Special lecture: "Teaching Southeast Asian History: Stories about the "Good" and the "Bad," Department of History, Peking University.

# **TEACHING** (recent only)

S. Rajaratnam School of International Studies (NTU), MSc Program. I taught a course titled "State, Society and Politics in the Philippines" in Academic Year (A/Y) 2015-16, Trimester 3; A/Y 2016-17, Trimester 1; A/Y 2017-18, Trimester 1; and A/Y 2018-19, Trimester 1.

# **GRADUATE STUDENTS MENTORED** (in alphabetical order)

Julius Bautista (ANU). 'Figuring Catholicism': The Santo Niño and Religious Discourse in Cebu (PhD, 2004); published as *Figuring Catholicism: An Ethnohistory of the Santo Niño de Cebu* (ADMU Press, 2010)

Nikki Serranilla Briones (NUS). From war dance to theatre of war: Moro-Moro performances in the Philippines (PhD, 2010); Winner of the Wang Gungwu Prize for best doctoral thesis)

Peter Burns (James Cook Univ.). 'The Leiden School' of Indonesian Studies (PhD, 1995)

Gloria Cano Garcia (NUS). The 'Spanish colonial past' in the construction of modern Philippine history (PhD, 2006)

HO Tzu Nyen (NUS). Afterimages: Strands of Modern Art in Singapore (MA, 2008)

Elizabeth Holt (James Cook University). American colonial representations of Filipinas (PhD, 1994); published as *Colonizing Filipinas: Nineteenth-century Representations of the Philippines in Western Historiography* (ADMU Press, 2002)

KOH Kim Seng (NUS). *Misunderstood Myanmar: An introspective study of the vicissitudes of a state in transition* (PhD, 2009, published in 2011)

Preciosa A. de Joya (NUS). In Search of Filipino Philosophy (PhD, 2014)

Kanami NAMIKI (NUS). Sayaw Filipino: A study of contrasting representations of Philippine culture (MA, 2007); published as *Ramon Obusan, Philippine Folkdance, and Me* (Anvil, 2014); winner of Philippine National Book Awards 2015 for non-fiction.

Ahmad Ali Nurdin (NUS). Islamic political parties in Malaysia and Indonesia (PhD, 2009)

Michael Poole (ANU). Western appropriation of Vietnamese literature (PhD, 2002)

Davisakd Puaksom (NUS). The pursuit of Java: Thai Panji stories, Melayu lingua franca, and the question of translation (PhD, 2008); winner of the Wang Gungwu prize for best doctoral thesis.

Takamichi SERIZAWA (NUS). Wartime Japanese Historical Writing on the Philippines (PhD, 2013)

SOON Chuan Yean (NUS). Popular politics in a Philippine municipality (PhD, 2008); published as *Tulong: An Articulation of Politics in the Christian Philippines* (UST Press 2016)

Eduardo C. Tadem (NUS). Peasants and outsiders: Change and continuity in three rural Philippine villages (PhD, 2006)

Trina P. Tinio (NUS). The triumph of Tagalog and the dominance of the discourse on English: Language politics in the Philippines during the American colonial period (PhD, 2009)